# **Amare Kassa**

# **Full-STACK DEVELOPER**

email address | Github | LinkedIn | Portfolio

#### **SUMMARY**

Experienced Full-stack developer proficient in Python, JavaScript, React, Redux, Django, and Rails. Prior experience in teaching computer science and engineering courses at Ethiopian Higher Educational institutions allowed for exploration of various computing areas before transitioning into software development. Possesses valuable skills in pair-programming, teamwork, collaboration, remote work, and effective communication.

#### **SKILLS**

Front-end: JavaScript, React, Redux, HTML5, CSS3

Back-end: Python, Django, Ruby, Rails, SQL, MySQL, PostgreSQL, SQLite

Tools & Methods: Git, GitHub, Gitflow, Netlify, Render, Mobile/Responsive Development, TDD, Firefox

Dev Tools, Jest, Rspec

Professional skills: Remote Pair-Programming, Teamwork, Mentoring, collaboration

**Leadership:** Chair-Computer Engineering

#### **EXPERIENCE**

HIGHLIGHTED TECHNICAL PROJECTS

Software | Full-Stack Developer Jan 2021 - Present

- •Understood intermediate and advanced topics in software and web development
- Developed web development projects together with teammates via remote pair programming, teamwork, and solo too
- Got professional skills on how to solve conflicts whenever a conflict between my coding partner and me occurs

<u>Detection-and-Classification-of-Transient-Execution-Attacks-Using-Performance-Counters</u>: This is a complex project by which transient execution attacks are detected and classified using Perceptron, written in Python programming language. Transient execution attacks occur when speculation execution instructions destined to be squashed are executed.

- Built with: (C++, Python)
- Tools used: ( Perf )

<u>Budget App</u>: Budget App is a mobile application that allows users to manage their expenses. It allows users to create an expense category, add their transaction to one of their categories, see the details for each transaction, see the total expenses for each category and for the whole category expenses.

Built with: (HTML5, CSS3, JavaScript, Rails)

<u>Car Reservation System</u>: Car Reservation System is a web application of which the back-end is built with Rails web framework and the Front-end is built with React library. It allows users to see the car models available, see the details of a car, reserve a car and cancel a car she/he reserved.

• Built with: (HTML5, CSS3, React, Redux, Rails)

MICROVERSE Inc.

Remote **Mentor (Volunteer)** Sep 2022 – Present

- Creating more awareness about Microverse and explaining about the tools they use daily.
- Providing help when they get stuck while doing projects.
- Providing help on professional experience at Microverse.

Debre Markos University, Debre Markos, Ethiopia

### Lecturer & Chair-Computer Engineering Oct 2016 - Jan 2021

- Prepared Computer and Network Security curriculum for undergraduate students. The curriculum got approved by the senate.
- Mentored and guided three students in developing high-quality projects that were chosen by the university's business incubation center, resulting in successful grant applications and funding.
- Selected as best performant chair among the four streams chair in the School of Electrical and Computer Engineering.

#### **EDUCATION**

MICROVERSE Aug 2022 - Present

## Remote Full Stack Web Development Program, Full Time

- Spent 1000+ hours mastering algorithms, data structures, and simultaneously developing web applications with HTML5, CSS3, JavaScript, and React/Redux, Ruby, Rails.
- Developed skills in remote pair-programming, teamwork, professional communication to the three teams (Morning sessions, Collaboration sessions, and Standup sessions) at Microverse.

National Taiwan University of Science and Technology (NTUST), Taipei, Taiwan Feb 2018 - Aug 2018 ( PhD scholarship in Electronic and Computer Engineering from NTUST, Taipei, Taiwan )

• Took courses for one semester: Software Defined Networking (SDN) and Network Function Virtualization (NFV), Modern Cryptography and Data Security, Advanced computer Architecture and organization, Seminar I: mainly on Machine Learning.

Addis Ababa University , Addis Ababa, Ethiopia

MSc., Computer Engineering Oct 2011 – July 2014

• Thesis: Detection and Control of DDoS Attacks Over Reputation-based Mobile Ad-hoc Networks.

Bahir Dar University, Bahir Dar, Ethiopia

BSc., Electrical & Computer Engineering Oct 2003 – Jul 2007

• Project: Traffic Light control system using z-8 microprocessor.